[
    {
        "question_number": "1",
        "question_text": " \n \nYou represent an individual applicant from Spain who has filed a European patent application \nin Spanish and satisfied all the requirements for filing. Examination was requested in Spanish \nat the time of filing the application. The examination and designation fees are due by 7 \nNovember 2023 and the applicant has asked you whether he is entitled to a reduction of 20% \nin the examination fee. What is the correct answer? \n \n \nA.​\nThe applicant is entitled to a reduction of 20% in the examination fee under Rule 6(3) \nEPC and Article 14(1) RFees. \n  \nB.​\nThe applicant is entitled to a reduction in the examination fee under Rule 6(3)EPC \nand Article 14(1) RFees, but the reduction is not 20%.",
        "answer": "The correct answer is B. \n  \nBeing a natural person, the applicant is entitled to the reduction under Rule 6(3)(b) EPC. \nAlso, the requirement for obtaining the fee reduction is fulfilled, since the request for \nexamination was requested in Spanish at the time of filing (Guidelines A-X, 9.2.3). The \nreduction as set out in Article 14(1) RFees is 30%."
    },
    {
        "question_number": "2",
        "question_text": " \n \nIs the following statement true or false? \n  \nWhen proceedings for grant of a European patent application are stayed following the \ninstitution of entitlement proceedings, renewal fees which fall due during the period of stay \ncan be paid up to the date of resumption of the proceedings for grant. \n  \nA.​\nTrue \nB.​\nFalse",
        "answer": "The correct answer is B, False.  \n \nIn the event of a stay of proceedings all periods other than those for the payment of renewal \nfees are interrupted (Rule 14(4) EPC, implementing Article 61(1) EPC). The application will \nlapse if the renewal fees are not paid. If the application has lapsed and it is adjudged that a \nperson other than the applicant is entitled to the grant of the European patent, that person \nmay still file a new European patent application in respect of the same invention under Article \n61(1)(b) EPC (G 3/92, headnote)."
    },
    {
        "question_number": "3",
        "question_text": " \n  \nYou represent a client whose European patent has been opposed. The opposition division \ndecides to maintain the patent in amended form. The invitation with the three-month time limit \nunder Rule 82(2) EPC is sent on 16 August 2021, but proceedings are interrupted under \nRule 142 EPC on 20 October 2021. The problems are resolved and the proceedings resume \non 16 January 2022. When does the time limit under Rule 82(2)EPC end? \n  \nA ​19 April 2022​\n  \nB ​30 April 2022",
        "answer": "The correct answer is A. \n  \nThe period begins again on the day on which the proceedings are resumed (Rule 142(4) \nEPC, implementing Article 120 EPC; Guidelines E-VII, 1.4). However, the new three-month \ntime limit under Rule 82(2) EPC expires during the Easter public holiday, when the EPO is \nclosed. The period is thus extended (Rule 134(1) EPC) until 19 April 2022 (Tuesday)."
    },
    {
        "question_number": "4",
        "question_text": " \n  \nYou are informed that one of the inventors named in an international application is incorrect. \nThe application names Mr Y, but the correct inventor is Mrs Z. ​\nWhat should you do? \n  \n1.​ Obtain the consent of Mr Y to rectification of the inventor before filing a request at the \nInternational Bureau with details of the correct inventor.​\n  \n2.​ File a request for rectification at the International Bureau with details of the correct \ninventor.",
        "answer": "The correct answer is B. \n  \nYou should file a request for rectification at the International Bureau with details of the correct \ninventor. Under Rule 92bis.1(a)(ii) PCT a change in the person, name or address of an \ninventor can be corrected provided the request is filed before the end of the 30-month period \nfrom the priority date (Rule 92bis.1(b) PCT and PCT Applicant’s Guide International Phase \n11.021). \n  \nUnder the PCT the consent of the person incorrectly designated as inventor is not needed. \n For a European patent application, the consent of the wrongly designated person is required \nfor correction (Rule 21(1) EPC)."
    },
    {
        "question_number": "5",
        "question_text": " \n​\nYour Client, A Inc, is a sub-licensee under European patent application EP-1. Can the \nsub-licence be recorded in the European Patent Register? \n  \nA​ No, it is not possible to record sub-licences in the European Patent Register.​\n  \nB​ Yes, any sub-licence can be recorded in the European Patent Register.​\n  \nC​ Yes, provided the licensee granting the sub-licence has recorded its licence in the \nEuropean Patent Register.",
        "answer": "The correct answer is C. \n  \nA sub-licence can only be recorded in the European Patent Register if it is granted by a \nlicensee whose licence is recorded in the Register (Rule 24(b) EPC, implementing Article 73 \nEPC)."
    },
    {
        "question_number": "6",
        "question_text": " \n  \nCompany C files a European patent application for an invention which has been displayed at \nan officially recognised international exhibition. The exhibition closes two weeks after the \ninvention was first displayed. Rule 25(d) EPC states that a suitable certificate must be filed \nwithin four months of the filing of the European patent application. Three months after filing \nthe application, the applicant approaches the authority responsible for the protection of \nindustrial property at the exhibition and obtains a certificate stating the information required \naccording to Rule 25 EPC. The certificate is filed within the four-month period together with \nthe authenticated identification of the invention. Will the certificate be accepted by the EPO? \n  \n1.​ No, the certificate was not issued at the exhibition.​\n  \n2.​ Yes, the certificate was filed within the specified four-month period.",
        "answer": "The correct answer is A. \n  \nThe correct answer is A, because the certificate was not issued at the exhibition. Article \n55(1)(b), 55(2) and Rule 25(a) EPC state that the certificate must be issued \nat the exhibition, so a certificate obtained after an exhibition is not acceptable."
    },
    {
        "question_number": "7",
        "question_text": " \nThe time limit for paying the examination fee for a European patent application ends on 18 \nAugust 2023. The applicant wishes to pay by bank transfer and wants to make absolutely \nsure that no additional fees have to be paid even if the payment is delayed due to unforeseen \ncircumstances. What can he do? \n1.​\nNothing. If the payment is received too late by the EPO it will be considered not to \nhave been made. \n2.​\nEffect the payment no later than 13 August 2023. \n3.​\nEffect the payment no later than 8 August 2023. \n4.​\nIt is sufficient to effect the payment on the last day for payment, that is on 18 August",
        "answer": "The correct answer is D.  \nThe payment is considered to have been made on the date when it is actually entered into an \nEPO bank account (Article 7(1) RFees). However, it is considered that the period for valid \npayment has been observed if payment is effected through a bank in a contracting state \nwithin the period in which the payment should have been made (Article 7(3) RFees), that is \nby 18 August 2023 (Friday) at the latest. The EPO may ask the party to provide evidence as \nto the date on which the payment was effected (Article 7(4) RFees).  \nThe current wording of Article 7 RFees applies to payments made on or after 1 April 2020. \nBefore that, if payment was made within the last ten days before expiry of the period, and \nreceived after the last day of the period, it was considered that the period had been observed \nif a surcharge of 10% was paid."
    },
    {
        "question_number": "8",
        "question_text": " \n \nA European patent application EP-A is refused in a decision dated 1 June 2023. Today is 15 \nJuly 2023. Is it still possible to file a divisional application from EP-A?  \nA.​\nYes. \nB.​\nNo. \nC.​\nOnly if the decision to refuse the application is appealed.",
        "answer": "Answer for"
    },
    {
        "question_number": "9",
        "question_text": " \n \nMost fees for European patent applications cannot be paid before their due date. One \nexception is renewal fees, which can always be paid up to: \nA.​\nThree months before the due date. \nB.​\nSix months before the due date. \nC.​\nOne year before the due date.",
        "answer": "The correct answer is A.  \nRenewal fees for European patent applications may be validly paid up to three months before \nthe due date. For the  renewal fee for the third year, answer B is also correct. This special \nrule for the 3rd renewal fee was made to allow for the payment of this fee on entry into the \nregional phase (Rule 51(1) EPC, implementing Article 86(1) EPC)."
    },
    {
        "question_number": "10",
        "question_text": " \nToday is 28 March 2023. Following national proceedings for entitlement of European patent \napplication EP-1, the successful party has elected to file a new application under Article \n61(1)(b) EPC. EP-1 was filed on 12 April 2019 and the new application, EP-2, was filed on 10 \nJanuary 2023.  What is the last day for paying the first renewal fee that is payable for the new \napplication, without surcharge (i.e. not including the fees for past renewals)? \n  \nA.​\n31 January 2023. \n  \nB.​\n2 May 2023.",
        "answer": "The correct answer is B.  \nThe first renewal fee for EP-2 (in respectof the 5th year) must be paid by 2 May 2023 \n(Tuesday). According to G 3/92 (Reasons 5.4), the filing date of EP-2 will be the filing date of \nEP-1, i.e. 12 April 2019. EP-2 was filed in the 4th year. According to Article 86(1) and Rule \n51(6) EPC no renewal fee for EP-2 needs to be paid in respect of the year in which it was \nfiled or any preceding year. The renewal fee for the 5th year is due (Article 86(1) and Rule \n51(1) EPC) on 30 April 2023 (Sunday), which is extended (Article 120 and Rule 134(1) EPC) \nto 2 May 2023 (Tuesday)."
    },
    {
        "question_number": "11",
        "question_text": " \nYou file a European patent application EP-1 in February 2023 on behalf of the applicant. In \nOctober 2023 you are informed that EP-1 should have claimed priority from United States \npatent application US-1 filed in March 2022. Is it possible to add the priority declaration to \nEP-1? \n  \nA.​\nNo. More than 16 months have elapsed since the filing of US-1. \nB.​\nYes. EP-1 was filed within 12 months of US-1, so is entitled to claim priority.",
        "answer": "The correct answer is A.  \n  \nThe time limit for adding a claim to priority has expired (Rule 52(2) EPC, implementing Article \n88(1) EPC; Guidelines A-III, 6.5.1). If the question had concerned a correction of a priority \nclaim that had already been made, the period could not expire before four months from the \nfiling date (Rule 52(3) EPC; Guidelines A-III, 6.5.2). In the current case, the four-month time \nlimit has also already expired."
    },
    {
        "question_number": "12",
        "question_text": " \n \nWhat is the legal effect of failing to file a priority document for a European patent application? \n  \n1.​ None. The priority document can be filed at any time.​\n  \n2.​ The European patent application will be deemed withdrawn if a priority \ndocument is not filed within 16 months of the earliest priority date (or any \nadditional period permitted by the EPO).​\n  \nThe right of priority will be lost if a priority document is not filed within 16 months of the \nearliest priority date (or any additional period permitted by the EPO).",
        "answer": "The correct answer is C.  \nIt is the right of priority that is lost if a priority document is not filed in due time (Rule 53(1) \nEPC, implementing Article 88(1) EPC: Rule 59 EPC, implementing Article 90(4) EPC; Article \n90(5) EPC)."
    },
    {
        "question_number": "13",
        "question_text": " \n \nEuropean patent application EP-1 is filed on 10 December 2020, but the inventor is not \ndesignated. The designation of the inventor is filed on 25 February 2022. Will the application \nbe refused? \n  \nA.​\nNo. The designation of the inventor was filed in due time. \nB.​\nYes. The designation of the inventor was not filed in due time.",
        "answer": "The correct answer is A. \nThe designation of the inventor was filed in due time.  \nThe designation of the inventor is due within 16 months (Rule 60(1) EPC, implementing \nArticle 90(4) EPC) of the filing date (–10 December 2020 - Thursday), but the period is \ndeemed to be observed if the information is communicated before completion of the technical \npreparations for the publication of the European patent application (five weeks before the end \nof the 18th month from the filing or priority date; Guidelines A-VI, 1.1  and Decision of the \nPresident, Special Edition No. 3, OJ EPO 2007, D.1). \n \nYou are receiving this newsletter because you've signed up on www.epo.org \nHaving trouble viewing this email? View it in your browser"
    },
    {
        "question_number": "14",
        "question_text": " \n \nIn response to an opposition, the patentee introduces the features of claim 12 as granted into \nclaim 1. Claim 12 was dependent on claim 1 and is phrased as a result to be achieved. The \nopponent argues that the amendment introduces a lack of clarity. Will the opposition division \nagree with the opponent? \n  \nA.​\nYes. A claim feature may not be phrased as a result to be achieved. \nB.​\nPerhaps. It depends on whether or not the feature phrased as a result to be achieved \nis considered to be clear. \nC.​\nNo. Since the feature was already in the claims set the amendment does not \nintroduce a lack of clarity.",
        "answer": "The correct answer is C. \nThe correct answer is C. Pursuant to G 3/14 the claims may be examined for compliance \nwith the requirements of Article 84 EPC only if and to the extent that the amendment \nintroduces non-compliance with Article 84. Since claim 1 as amended corresponds to claim \n12 as granted, no such non-compliance has been introduced."
    },
    {
        "question_number": "15",
        "question_text": " \n \nWhy might an opposition be filed even if the European patent has been surrendered, or has \nlapsed, in all the designated contracting states (Rule 75 EPC)?",
        "answer": "There are two correct answers, A and C. \n  \nThere are occasions where the difference between lapse/surrender  \nand revocation are important, for example where licence payments depend on the existence \nof a patent (or application).  \n  \nThe two correct answers simply use different terminology for the same situation."
    },
    {
        "question_number": "16",
        "question_text": " \n \nIn opposition proceedings a patent proprietor has proposed amendments to claims 1, 3 and 4 \nof its patent to overcome issues of novelty and inventive step. The proprietor has also noted \na problem with the clarity of claim 2 and has additionally proposed an amendment to this \nclaim. Is the amendment of claim 2 permitted? \n  \n1.​\nYes \n2.​\nNo",
        "answer": "The correct answer is B.  \nAmendment of claim 2 is not permitted because the amendment is not occasioned by a \nground for opposition (since clarity is not a ground for opposition as specified by Article 100 \nEPC) (Rule 80 EPC, implementing Article 101(1) EPC)."
    },
    {
        "question_number": "17",
        "question_text": " \n \nWhere an assumed infringer intervenes in opposition appeal proceedings, which of the \nfollowing fees are payable? \n  \nA.​\nThe opposition fee. \nB.​\nThe appeal fee. \nC.​\nThe opposition fee and the appeal fee. \nD.​\nThe assumed infringer must pay the opposition fee and may choose whether to pay \nthe appeal fee.",
        "answer": "The correct answer is A.  \n  \nIn the case of an intervention at the appeal stage only the opposition fee is payable. Payment \nof the opposition fee is required by Rule 89(2) EPC (implementing Article 105(1) EPC). The \nEPO has no provisions for requiring the payment of an appeal fee in such cases (G 3/04, \nReasons 11). \n  \nThis means that if the notice of intervention is filed during appeal proceedings, the intervener \ncan only obtain status as an opponent and not as an appellant.  He will be party to the appeal \nproceedings as of right."
    },
    {
        "question_number": "18",
        "question_text": " \n \nDuring proceedings before the opposition division there is a valid intervention under Article \n105 EPC. At the conclusion of the proceedings the patent is maintained in amended form. Is \nthe assumed infringer permitted to appeal? \n  \nA.​\nYes \nB.​\nNo",
        "answer": "The correct answer is A.  \nThe assumed infringer is entitled to file an appeal in this case, because they became a party \nduring opposition proceedings (G 3/04, Reasons 4, 10 and 11; Article105(2) EPC - the \nassumed infringer acquires the status of an opponent)."
    },
    {
        "question_number": "19",
        "question_text": " \n \nA patent proprietor requests revocation under Article 105a EPC of its European patent EP-B, \nwhich has been validated in Germany, France and Spain. It has an exclusive licensee in \nGermany. Will the request for revocation be considered to be admissible? \n  \nA.​\nNo, the patent proprietor must file evidence that it is entitled to act on behalf of the \nexclusive licensee. \nB.​\nYes, the existence of an exclusive licensee has no bearing on the admissibility of the \nrequest for revocation.",
        "answer": "The correct answer is B.   \nAccording to Rule 92(2)(c) EPC (implementing Article 105a(1) EPC), such evidence \nis only required where the requester is not the proprietor in all the relevant contracting \nstates. An exclusive licensee has no corresponding rights."
    },
    {
        "question_number": "20",
        "question_text": " \n \nThe applicant for European patent application EP-1 has granted an exclusive license under \nthe application. The exclusive licensee wishes to make its rights known by recording the \nlicense in the European Patent Register.  \nIs it possible to record the exclusive license? \n  \nA.​\nNo, exclusive licenses cannot be recorded in the European Patent Register. \nB.​\nYes, exclusive licenses can be recorded in the European Patent Register at the joint \nrequest of both the applicant and the licensee. \nC.​\nYes, exclusive licenses can be recorded in the European Patent Register, but only by \nthe applicant.  \nD.​\nYes, exclusive licences can be recorded in the European Patent Register by either the \napplicant or the licensee.",
        "answer": "The correct answer is B.   \nExclusive licenses can only be recorded in the European Patent Register (Article 127 and \nRule 143(1)(w) EPC) if both the applicant and the licensee so request (Rule 24(a) EPC, \nimplementing Article 73 EPC; Guidelines E-XIV, 6.1)."
    },
    {
        "question_number": "21",
        "question_text": " \nA European patent application is filed on 13.01.2023, not claiming priority. After receiving the \nEESR, the applicant wishes to proceed as soon as possible with examination and therefore \npays the examination fee, responds to the search opinion and files by fax a request for \naccelerated examination under PACE. Will the EPO start examination as soon as possible? \nAnd will examination be accelerated? \n  \nA.​\nExamination will start but will not be accelerated. \nB.​\nExamination will not start until the time limit for requesting examination but then it will \nbe accelerated. \nC.​\nExamination will start early and will be accelerated. \nD.​\nNo.",
        "answer": "The correct answer is A. \n The responsibility for examining the application passes to the examining division when a \nrequest for examination is filed. The applicant must also respond to the search opinion before \na communication from the examining division can be issued. However, requests for \naccelerated proceedings must be filed online using the dedicated request form, so the filing \nof the request by fax will not be accepted (Guidelines C-II, 1 and 3; Guidelines E-VIII, 4; \nNotice of the EPO dated 30 November 2015 concerning ways to expedite the European \ngrant procedure, OJ EPO 2015, A94)."
    },
    {
        "question_number": "22",
        "question_text": " \n \nIt is permitted to file observations under Article 115 EPC in respect of a patent undergoing \nlimitation proceedings. However, there is no provision under Article 105b EPC or Rule 95 \nEPC for examination as to patentability,  \nand Article 115 EPC specifically refers to observations concerning patentability.  \nIs there any reason why a third party might nevertheless file observations under Article 115 \nEPC in respect of a patent undergoing limitation proceedings? \n  \n1.​\nYes, the examining division may be persuaded to consider patentability as part of the \nlimitation proceedings. \n2.​\nYes, patentability can be considered in the broader sense as including issues relating \nto Articles 84 and 123(2) EPC. \n3.​\nNo, there is no point in filing observations on patentability because they will not be \ntaken into consideration.",
        "answer": "The correct answer is B. \nAccording to Guidelines D-X, 4.3, patentability, at least in limitation proceedings, is to be \ninterpreted as including issues under ​\nArticles 84 and 123(2) EPC."
    },
    {
        "question_number": "23",
        "question_text": " \n \nIn response to a Rule 71(3) communication you have filed, on the 2 April 2023, the required \ntranslations of the claims and paid the grant fee. Today, the 3 May 2023, you receive the \ndecision to grant, dated 28 April 2023. The decision states that the mention of the grant will \nbe published on the 24 May 2023. What is/was the last day a divisional application may be \nfiled? \n  \nA.​\n2 April 2023 \nB.​\n28 April 2023 \nC.​\n8 May 2023 \nD.​\n23 May 2023 \nE.​\n24 May 2023",
        "answer": "The correct answer is D. \n A divisional application can be filed on any pending application (Rule 36(1) implementing Art. \n76 EPC). An application is pending up to (but not including) the date that the European \nPatent Bulletin mentions the grant of the patent (G 1/09, Guidelines A-IV, 1.1.1). Therefore, \nthe last day the parent application is pending is the 23 May 2023."
    },
    {
        "question_number": "24",
        "question_text": " \n \nIn the case of applicants entitled to a fee reduction under Rule 6(3) EPC, does the fee \nreduction include the additional fee for pages in excess of 35? \n  \nA.​\nYes \nB.​\nNo",
        "answer": "The correct answer is A.  \n  \nThe applicant is also entitled to a fee reduction for pages in excess of 35 (Guidelines A-X, \n9.2.2). The additional fee is part of the filing fee (Article 2(1a) RFees)."
    },
    {
        "question_number": "25",
        "question_text": " \n \nClaim 1 of European patent application EP-1 relates to a water-disposable and flushable \nabsorbent article. It is amended to specify that each of first and second fibrous assemblies is \na wet-laid tissue. The only passage in the application as filed mentioning that either of the \nfirst or the second fibrous  \nassembly may be a wet-laid tissue is the following: “Either the first or the second fibrous \nassembly may be a wet-laid tissue. In this case, the wet-laid tissues must have apertures or \nbe provided with fibrils.” Is the amendment to claim 1 likely to be allowable under \nArticle123(2) EPC? \n  \nA.​\nYes \nB.​\nNo",
        "answer": "The amendment is not allowable under Article 123(2) EPC because the first fibrous assembly \nis disclosed in the application as filed as being a wet-laid tissue only in combination \nwith other features not present in the claim.​\n  \nThe amendment is therefore an intermediate generalisation of the originally disclosed \ntechnical information which in this case lacks support in the application as filed (Guidelines \nH-V, 3.2.1 and T 1164/04)"
    },
    {
        "question_number": "26",
        "question_text": " \n \nClaim 1 of European patent application EP-1 originally defines a polymer blend XY \ncontaining, as a filler, graphite, talc, asbestos or silica.  \nThe European search report identifies prior art disclosing a polymer blend XY containing \nasbestos. Is it permissible under Article 123(2) EPC to restrict the list of fillers by simply \nomitting asbestos, i.e., to claim a polymer blend XY containing, as a filler, graphite, talc or \nsilica? \n  \nA.​\nYes \nB.​\nNo",
        "answer": "The correct answer is A.  \n  \nIt is permissible to delete parts of the claimed subject-matter if the \ncorresponding embodiments were originally described, for example, as alternatives in a \nclaim (as here) or as embodiments explicitly set out in the description. In this case, the scope \nof the original claim could be seen as four alternative claims and the amendment simply \nexcludes one of these alternatives. It is generally not permissible to delete items from more \nthan one list of alternatives (Guidelines H-V, 3.3)."
    },
    {
        "question_number": "27",
        "question_text": " \n \nIn which of the following situations must an authorization be filed? \nWhat will be the consequence if an authorisation is not filed in due time? \n  \nA.​\nAn authorised representative files a new European patent application.  \nB.​\nAn employee files an opposition on behalf of their employer. \nC.​\nA legal practitioner who is not an employee of the applicant files a new European \npatent application. \nD.​\nAn authorised representative takes over representation in a previously filed European \npatent application. \nE.​\nAn authorised representative files an international application with the EPO as \nreceiving office. \nF.​\nAn authorised representative withdraws a priority claim in an international application.",
        "answer": "Authorisations are needed for B, D and F but not normally for A, C and E. \n  \nFor the EPO, signed authorisations must be filed on request and it is up to the EPO to \nrequest them (Guidelines A-VIII, 1.6).  \n  \nRe: A and D: For professional representatives authorisation will only be requested in certain \ncases, and not normally for newly filed EP applications. The situation in D, where an \nauthorised representative takes over the prosecution of a previously filed European \napplication, is one of the special cases where an authorisation is required (Decision of the \nPresident dated 12 July 2007, Special Edition No. 3, OJ EPO 2007, L.1). \n  \nRe: B and C: Authorisations are required for employees representing their employer (Article \n133(3) EPC) and for legal practitioners acting in accordance with Article 134(8) EPC \n(Guidelines A-VIII, 1.3, 1.5 and 1.8). However, the filing of a new patent application is \nexempted from this requirement (Rule 152(6) EPC and Decision of the President of the EPO \ndated 12 July 2007). \n  \nRe: E and F: According to Rule 90.1 PCT a person acting as agent must be appointed. This \nmust be done by all applicants either signing the request or a separate power of attorney \n(Rule 90.4(a) PCT). Any RO, ISA, SISA or IPEA may waive the requirement, and the EPO \nhas submitted such a waiver (PCT Applicant’s Guide, International Phase Introduction, \nAnnex C: EPO). Hence, for filing an international application with the EPO as RO no \nauthorisation is needed. However, Rule 90.4(e) PCT says that a power of attorney is always \nneeded for any notice of withdrawal, including withdrawal of a priority claim (PCT Applicant’s \nGuide, International phase, 5.044 and 5.045). \n  \nIn each case, if the authorisation is not filed in due time, any action that must be performed \nby a representative will be considered not to have been performed. The actual consequence \nwill vary depending on the action."
    },
    {
        "question_number": "28",
        "question_text": " \n \nErrors and mistakes in any document filed with the European Patent Office may be corrected \non request under Rule 139 EPC. What is the last date in written proceedings prior to grant \nthat such a request can be made? \n  \nA.​\nUp to the time the decision to grant has been received by the applicant or their \nrepresentative. \nB.​\nUp to the time the decision to grant has been handed over to the EPO internal postal \nservice. \nC.​\nUp to the expiry of the time limit for replying to the communication under Rule 71(3) \nEPC.",
        "answer": "The correct answer is B \n  \nUp to the time the decision to grant (Rule 71a(1) EPC) is handed over to \nthe EPO's internal postal service (G 12/91; Guidelines H-VI, 2.1).  \nThis date can be found in the lower right-hand corner of any decision letter from the EPO. \nPrevious practice was that the date of the decision was three days before the date of the \ncommunication, but that is not the case anymore. The date is printed at the bottom of the \ndecision to grant form (Form 2006A)."
    },
    {
        "question_number": "29",
        "question_text": " \n \nOn receipt of the decision to grant its European patent application EP-1 under Rule 71a(1) \nEPC the applicant realizes that they have made a significant typographical error in claim 1.  \nWhat action can they take before the EPO to correct the error? \n  \nA.​\nNone \nB.​\nSeek correction under Rule 140 EPC \nC.​\nSeek correction under Rule 139 EPC",
        "answer": "The correct answer is A.  \n  \nNo action can be taken to correct a typographical error at this stage. Correction under \nRule139 EPC is only possible up to the time the decision is handed over to the EPO's \ninternal postal service (Guidelines H-VI, 2.1). Rule 140 EPC is only available to correct errors \nin decisions of the EPO, and not to correct errors in documents filed by a patent applicant or \nproprietor (G 1/10). Where appropriate, correction may be possible after grant by way of \nlimitation or opposition proceedings, but any amendment must comply with Article 123(2) \nand (3) EPC."
    },
    {
        "question_number": "30",
        "question_text": " \n \nCompany X wishes to file an opposition to European patent EP-B, which was recently \ngranted to its main competitor, company Y. To avoid retaliation, company X would prefer not \nto file the opposition in its own name. It therefore asks a European patent attorney to file the \nopposition in her name. Will the EPO accept this? \n  \nA.​ Yes  \nB.​ No \nC.​ Only if the patentee does not object",
        "answer": "The correct answer is A.  \nIt is permissible to file an opposition in one’s own name while acting on behalf of a third party \n(G 3/97 and G 4/97). The only two situations that might be considered abuse of process \nwould be if the opponent was acting on behalf of the proprietor, company Y, or the opponent \nwas de facto acting as a professional representative without being qualified. Since in this \ncase the attorney is a qualified European patent attorney acting on behalf of company X, this \nsituation does not arise. \nCompany X will not be party to the proceedings so it will be dependent on the representative \nduring opposition proceedings."
    },
    {
        "question_number": "31",
        "question_text": " \n \nEuropean patent EP-B is granted with a claim directed to a method of operating a heart \npacemaker in dependence upon the required cardiac output while a person is exercising, the \npacemaker including a pressure sensing means mounted on a pacing lead and adapted to \nbe implanted in a heart and used to sense the right ventricular systolic pressure, which \npressure is used to control the pacer rate. Is it permissible in opposition or opposition appeal \nproceedings to amend the claim to be directed to a heart pacemaker in order to address \nproblems relating to Article 53(c) EPC? \n \nA.​\nYes, a change in claim category is permitted. \n  \nB.​\nNo, a change in claim category would contravene Article 123(3) EPC.",
        "answer": "The correct answer is B.  \nA change in claim category from a method of operating a device to the device itself, i.e. \ndeleting the “method features” defining therapeutic operation of the device, \nwould broaden the claim and contravene Article 123(3) EPC (Guidelines H-V, 7.3). The \nfeatures of the pacemaker as defined in the device claim do not depend on the \ncircumstances of its operation, but they did under the terms of the prior method claim (“while \na person is exercising”). If the original claim contains the claimed features of the device \nexhaustively, the change of category may be allowable (Guidelines H-V, 7.3). This condition \nis not fulfilled.  \nMethod features relating to how the pacemaker is installed in and interacts with the human \nbody cannot be converted to device features, amongst other things because an “adapted to” \ntype formulation does not confer the same limitation. For example, a “pressure sensing \nmeans adapted to sense the right ventricular systolic pressure” is not limited to such use, \nsince it can e.g. be used to sense the left ventricular systolic pressure (T 82/93, Reasons 2.2 \nand 2.3)."
    },
    {
        "question_number": "32",
        "question_text": " \n \nThe first communication from the examining division concerning a European patent \napplication is unexpectedly negative. The applicant decides not to proceed further with the \napplication. Can the applicant get a refund of fees in this situation? \n  \nA.​ Yes \nB.​ No",
        "answer": "The correct answer is A. \n  \n50% of the examination fee will be refunded if the patent application is withdrawn after \nsubstantive examination has begun but before the expiry of the time limit for replying to the \nfirst communication. To get the refund, the applicant must actively withdraw the application \nbefore the time limit for reply (Article 11(b) RFees)."
    },
    {
        "question_number": "33",
        "question_text": " \n \nYou file an international application for an applicant on 6 November 2023, but do not pay the \nfees because the applicant wishes to delay paying them as long as possible. The fees are \ndue by 6 December 2023, but are not paid until 11 December 2023. What is the most likely \noutcome? \n  \nA.​\nThe international application will be considered to be withdrawn. \nB.​\nThe fees will be accepted as if they had been paid within the one-month period. \nC.​\nThe applicant will be sent an invitation to pay a late payment fee of 50% of the fees \ndue.",
        "answer": "The correct answer is B.  \n  \nThe fees will be accepted as if they had been paid within the one-month period. This \nis because it is extremely unlikely that the receiving office will have issued an invitation to pay \nthe fees originally due together with the late payment fee (Rule 16bis.1 PCT) by 11 \nDecember 2023 and any payment made before the issue of the invitation is considered to \nhave been made in due time (PCT Applicant's Guide International Phase 5.193 and 5.194)."
    },
    {
        "question_number": "34",
        "question_text": " \n \nTwo applicants resident in Germany jointly file an international application with the EPO as \nreceiving office. No agent or common representative is appointed. Following receipt of the \ninternational search report, the applicants both agree that the international application should \nbe withdrawn, so the first-named applicant on Form PCT/RO/101 sends a letter, signed by \nhim, to the EPO as receiving office specifically withdrawing the international application. Will \nthe application be withdrawn? \n  \nA.​\nNo \nB.​\nYes",
        "answer": "The correct answer is A.  \nThe international application will not be withdrawn. Pursuant to Rule 90bis.1 PCT, the \napplicant may withdraw the international application at any time prior to the expiry of 30 \nmonths from the priority date. In the case of multiple applicants, one applicant cannot act on \ntheir own. Any withdrawal requires the signature of all the applicants, or that of an agent or \ncommon representative who has been explicitly appointed by all the applicants. A deemed \ncommon representative (as in this case) is not entitled to sign a notice of withdrawal on \nbehalf of the other applicant (Rule 90bis.5 PCT and PCT Applicant's Guide International \nPhase 11.048)."
    },
    {
        "question_number": "35",
        "question_text": " \n \nThe applicant for international application PCT-1 wishes to prevent publication of the \napplication. What is the last day for withdrawing the application and  \npreventing publication? \n \nA.​\nThe 15th day prior to the date of publication. \nB.​\nAny time prior to the date of publication. \nC.​\nThe end of the day five weeks before the end of the 18th month from the priority or \nfiling date as appropriate.",
        "answer": "The correct answer is A.  \nApplicants can prevent publication if the international application is withdrawn before the \ntechnical preparations for publication have been completed (Article 21.5 PCT; PCT \nApplicant's Guide International Phase 11.048 and 11.049) and the technical preparations for \npublication are deemed completed by the 15th day prior to the date of publication (PCT \nApplicant's Guide International Phase 9.014)."
    },
    {
        "question_number": "36",
        "question_text": " \n \nYou are the agent for international application PCT-1. Shortly before the end of the \ninternational phase the applicant informs you that they wish to continue only with the regional \nphase before the EPO and additionally that there was an error in the details of the inventor \nand that the correct inventor is Ms White and not Mr Black. They ask you whether it would be \nbetter to wait until entry  \ninto the EPO regional phase rather than to rush correction of the inventorship details in the \ninternational phase. What is your advice? \n  \nA.​\nInventorship should be corrected if at all possible in the international phase. \nB.​\nIt would be better to wait until after entry into the EPO regional phase. \nC.​\nThere is no difference between the two options.",
        "answer": "The correct answer is A. \n  \nAlthough it should also be possible to correct the inventor's details in the ​\nEPO regional phase, this requires the consent of the wrongly-named inventor \n(Rule 21(1) EPC), while in the international phase no such consent is required (Rule 92bis.1 \nPCT; PCT Applicant's Guide International Phase 11.018 - 11.020)."
    },
    {
        "question_number": "37",
        "question_text": " \n \nYou are monitoring the progress of an international application and on reviewing the details \nof the international search report you realize that you know of relevant prior art that has not \nbeen cited in the search report, but which is likely to be novelty-destroying in respect of at \nleast some of the claims.  \nYou believe that the international application will enter the national or regional phase in a \nsignificant number of countries or regions and it would therefore be time-consuming and \ncostly to file separate observations in respect of each of  \nthe national or regional applications. What can you do? \n  \nA.​\nFile observations online using ePCT. \nB.​\nSend a letter with your observations to the receiving office or the International \nBureau. \nC.​\nFile observations by letter. \nD.​\nIt is not possible to file observations on international applications.",
        "answer": "The correct answer is A.  \n  \nIt is possible to file observations online using ePCT. Submissions made in any other \nway will not normally be treated as observations. It is up to the individual offices to decide \nwhat use to make of the ePCT observations (PCT Applicant's Guide International \nPhase 11.109 – 11.117)."
    },
    {
        "question_number": "38",
        "question_text": " \n \nThe EPO as receiving office issues an invitation to the applicant to remedy certain defects in \nan international application within a time limit of two months from the date of invitation. The \ninvitation is dated as being mailed on 22 September 2023 and is received by the applicant on \n2 October 2023. What is the final date for responding to the invitation? \n  \nA.​\n22 November 2023 \nB.​\n27 November 2023 \nC.​\n3 December 2023 \nD.​\n4 December 2023",
        "answer": "The correct answer is B, 27 November 2023.  \n  \nThe invitation was received ten days after mailing, i.e. three days later than the seven days of \nRule 80.6 PCT, so the period expires three days later than two months from the mailing date, \nthat is, on 25 November 2023, which is a Saturday. The final date for responding is \ntherefore 27 November 2023 (Monday) (Rule 80.5(i) PCT)."
    },
    {
        "question_number": "39",
        "question_text": " \n \nInternational application PCT-1 is filed on 31 October 2023. It seeks to claim priority from \nEuropean patent application EP-1 filed on 27 October 2022. Can the claim to priority be \nrestored in the international phase so as to be effective in a subsequent EPO regional \nphase? \n  \nA.​\nNo, the 12-month period has expired. \nB.​\nYes, the applicant can request further processing. \nC.​\nYes, the applicant can restore the priority claim provided that they can show that the \ndate was missed unintentionally. \nD.​\nYes, the applicant can restore the priority date provided that they  \ncan show that they were unable, despite taking all due care, to meet the time limit for \nclaiming priority.",
        "answer": "The correct answer is D.  \n  \nFurther processing can only be requested before the EPO in the regional phase and is ruled \nout for the priority period (Article 121(4) EPC). In the international phase the applicant can \nrestore the right of priority (Rule 26bis.3(a) PCT; PCT Applicant’s Guide International Phase \n5.062-5.068). ​\nAlthough the \"unintentional\" criterion is applicable in some countries, the EPO applies the \n\"all due care\" criterion of Rule 26bis.3(a)(i) PCT and will apply this in accordance with its \nestablished practice under Article 122 EPC and Rule 136 EPC (PCT Applicant’s Guide \nNational Phase, Annex: National Chapter, EP Annex C and Euro-PCT Guide 15th edition, \n2022, 5.13.017 – 5.13.020)."
    },
    {
        "question_number": "40",
        "question_text": " \n \nYou receive an email on 30 October 2023 from a United States patent \nattorney asking you to enter the regional phase before the EPO in respect of \ninternational application PCT-1. The international application was filed at the United States \nPatent and Trademark Office on 14 March 2022 claiming priority from United States \npatent application US-1 filed 14 March 2021. Can you effect entry into the EPO regional \nphase? \n  \nA.​ No, the 31-month period has expired. \nB.​ Yes, provided the priority of US-1 is withdrawn. \nC.​ Yes, provided use is made of the provisions for further processing.",
        "answer": "The correct answer is C.  \nThe EPO regional phase can still be entered provided use is made of further processing. The \n31-month period expired on 14 October 2023 (Saturday, extended to 16 October 2023). \nSince the 31-month time limit was not met, the EPO will issue a communication to the \napplicant under Rule 160(2) EPC and there will be a two-month period for entry into the EPO \nregional phase using further processing (Article 121(1) and Rule 135 EPC). On 30 October, \nthe client is therefore well within the two-month period for requesting further processing. It is \nnot necessary to wait for the communication to be issued, but the further processing fee must \nstill be paid in addition to the other fees and acts for entry into the EPO regional phase.  \nAlternative B is not an option (and would also have been less preferable). It is only possible \nto withdraw a priority claim in an international application prior to the expiry of 30 months \nfrom the (earliest) priority date (Rule 90bis.3(a) PCT)."
    },
    {
        "question_number": "41",
        "question_text": " \n \nInternational patent application PCT-1 is filed on 16 June 2019 without any claim to priority. \nSteps are taken to enter the EPO regional phase on 26 December 2021. When should the \nrenewal fee in respect of the third year be paid (without surcharge)? \n  \nA.​\n30 June 2021 \nB.​\n26 December 2021 \nC.​\n2 January 2022 \nD.​\n16 January 2022 \nE.​\n17 January 2022",
        "answer": "The correct answer is E, 17 January 2022.  \nThe renewal fee must be paid within 31 months of the filing date of PCT-1 (Rule 159(1)(g) \nEPC). 16 January 2022 is a Sunday, so the fee is due by Monday, 17 January 2022 under \nRule 134(1) EPC (J 1/81; Guidelines A-X, 5.2.4).  \nNote that in this case the fee is due on the actual date and not at the end of the month in \nwhich the 31-month period expires."
    },
    {
        "question_number": "42",
        "question_text": " \n \nInternational application PCT-1 was filed by applicant A on 5 January 2020 and the \nrequirements for entry into the European regional phase were completed on 19 July 2022. \nEuropean patent application EP-1 was filed by applicant B on 19 June 2022 validly claiming \npriority from Italian patent application IT-1 filed on 20 June 2021. PCT-1, EP-1 and IT-1 all \nrelate to the same invention. What is the prior art effect of PCT-1 on EP-1? \n  \nA.​\nPCT-1 has no prior art effect on EP-1. \nB.​\nPCT-1 will be part of the state of the art according to Article 54(3) EPC. \nC.​\nPCT-1 will be part of the state of the art according to Article 54(2) EPC.",
        "answer": "The correct answer is B.  \nPCT-1 will be part of the state of the art within the meaning of Article 54(3) EPC due to its \nearlier filing date (Article 153(5) EPC and Rule 165 EPC).  \nThe relevant dates are shown in the timeline below. PCT-1 was published promptly 18 \nmonths after 5 January 2020 (provided that the applicant of PCT-1 did not request early \npublication under Article 21(2)(b) PCT), thus promptly after 5 July 2021  (Article 21(2)(a) PCT \nand Rule 48 PCT), that is on the following Thursday, i.e. on 8 July 2021 (PCT Applicant’s \nGuide International Phase 9.013). This is later than the priority date of EP-1 of 20 June 2021. \nPCT-1 is therefore not comprised in the state of the art within the meaning of Article 54(2) \nEPC for EP-1."
    },
    {
        "question_number": "43",
        "question_text": " \n \nInternational application PCT-1 enters the European regional phase as EP-1 today. \nIndependent claims 1 and 10 of the international application were considered to lack unity in \nthe international phase and a partial search report was drawn up by the EPO as ISA in \nrespect of the invention of claim 1.  The applicant wishes to have the opportunity to protect \nthe invention of claim 10 during the EPO regional phase, but wants to keep costs to a \nminimum, at least at the beginning. What can the applicant do? \n  \nA.​\nFile a divisional application to the invention of independent claim 10 after entry into \nthe EPO regional phase. \nB.​\nPay an additional search fee in respect of the invention of independent claim 10 \nwithin two months of entry into the EPO regional phase. \nC.​\nPay an additional search fee in respect of the invention of independent claim 10 \nwithin two months of notification by the EPO.",
        "answer": "The correct answer is C (Rule 164(2) EPC).  \n If the examining division still considers that there is lack of unity, it will send a notification \n(Rule 164(2)(a) EPC).   \n It is possible that the EPO may regard the claims as satisfying the requirements of Article 82 \nEPC, in which case no further search fee will be required. In this case, for answer B, the \nadditional search fee would have been paid without a legal basis and would be refunded by \nthe EPO (guidelines A-X, 10.1.1), although this might take some time. \n Answer A would work, but involves additional costs."
    },
    {
        "question_number": "44",
        "question_text": " \n \nGenerally speaking, oral proceedings must be held if any party to proceedings so requests. \nThis does not apply to requests for further oral proceedings  \nbefore the same department where the parties and the subject of the proceedings are the \nsame. Are there any other situations in which the EPO may refuse a request for oral \nproceedings? \n  \nA.​\nThere are no further exceptions. \nB.​\nThe receiving section may refuse a request for oral proceedings. \nC.​\nThe opposition division may refuse a request for oral proceedings. \nD.​\nThe Legal Division may refuse a request for oral proceedings.",
        "answer": "The correct answer is  B.  \n \nThe receiving section may refuse a request for oral proceedings. ​\nAccording to Article 116(2) EPC, the receiving section is only required to accede to a \nrequest for oral proceedings if it considers this to be expedient or if it intends to refuse the \nEuropean patent application."
    },
    {
        "question_number": "45",
        "question_text": " \n \nEntry into the European phase of an international application can be effected early provided \nan express request for early processing is made at the time the requirements of Rule 159(1) \nEPC are complied with. International application PCT-1 was filed 28 months ago with no \nclaim to priority. The application consists of 20 pages, including 16 claims. The international \nsearch was carried out by the EPO acting as ISA and the international search report was \npublished with the international application. Which of the following fees must be paid in order \nto effect early entry into the European phase? \n  \nA.​\nThe filing fee. \nB.​\nThe filing fee, the examination fee and the designation fee. \nC.​\nThe filing fee, the examination fee, the designation fee and the renewal fee. \nD.​\nThe filing fee, the claims fee, the examination fee, the designation fee and the \nrenewal fee.",
        "answer": "The correct answer is C.   \nThe claims fee (Euro-PCT Guide 15th edition, 2022, 5.11.04) can be paid up to expiry of the \nperiod under Rule 162(2) EPC (Guidelines E-IX, 2.3.8)."
    },
    {
        "question_number": "46",
        "question_text": " \n \nInternational application PCT-1 was not filed within 12 months of its priority application, the \npriority period being missed by 25 days. The applicant filed a request for restoration of the \npriority right at the receiving office and this was granted under the \"unintentional\" criterion \nbefore publication of the international application. \nThe applicant realises that this is not sufficient for the EPO to grant restoration of the priority \nright and asks you to file a request for restoration after entry  \ninto the EPO regional phase. When does the request for restoration have to be filed at the \nEPO \nA.​\nWithin one month of the expiry of 31 months from the filing date of the priority right to \nbe restored. \nB.​\nWithin one month of the date on which the requirements of Rule 159(1) EPC are \nsatisfied. \nC.​\nWithin two months of the date on which the requirements of  \nRule 159(1) EPC are satisfied. \nD.​\nWithin one month of the expiry of 31 months from the filing date of  \nthe international application.",
        "answer": "The correct answer is A, within one month of the expiry of 31 months from the filing date of \nthe priority right to be restored.  \nAccording to Rule 26bis.2(c)(iii) PCT a priority claim will not be considered void simply \nbecause the international application has a filing date which is later than the date on which \nthe priority period expired, provided that the filing date is within two months of that date. \nConsequently, the 31-month period expires 31 months from the priority date to be restored. A \nperiod of one month is permitted for filing a request for restoration of priority at the EPO \nunder Rule 49ter.2(b)(i) PCT and Article 22 PCT. \nMerely fulfilling the requirements of Rule 159(1) earlier than 31 months from the priority date \nwill not change this, as the EPO can only start processing the application before the \n31-month time limit if this is expressly requested by the applicant. If the applicant requests \nearly processing and complies with the requirements of Rule 159(1), the effective date of \nearly entry will change, and the time limit for requesting restoration of the priority period will \nbe one month from the effective date (Euro-PCT Guide, 15th edition, 2022, 5.13.022 – \n5.13.023; Guidelines E-IX, 2.8.)"
    },
    {
        "question_number": "47",
        "question_text": " \n \nInternational application PCT-1 claims priority from Korean utility model  \napplication KR-U1. Is a translation of the priority document required on  \nentry into the European regional phase? \n  \nA.​\nA translation into the language of the proceedings is required within two months of the \nend of the 31-month period for entering  \nthe EPO regional phase. \nB.​\nA translation into one of the official EPO languages is required within two months of \nthe end of the 31-month period for entering the EPO regional phase. \nC.​\nNo translation is required unless the validity of the priority claim is relevant to \npatentability. \nD.​\nNo translation is required if a declaration is submitted that the European patent \napplication is a complete translation of the priority application.",
        "answer": "The correct answer is C.  \nNo translation is required unless the validity of the priority claim is relevant to patentability \n(Rule 51bis.1(e)(i) PCT; PCT Applicant’s Guide National Phase 5.010).  \nAnswer D is also correct. If the priority claim becomes relevant to patentability, a declaration \nthat the European patent application is a complete translation of the priority application may \nbe made instead (Guidelines A-III, 6.8.6). Note that a certified copy of the priority document \nitself must always be provided, except in those cases where the EPO will include a copy of \nthe previous application without such a request (Guidelines A-III, 6.7).  If the previous \napplication is a Chinese, Korean or United States application, the EPO will include a copy of \nthe previous application free of charge if the European patent application was filed before 1 \nJanuary 2022 or, in the case of a Euro-PCT application that has entered the European phase \nbefore that date, if the required priority document can be included in the file of the application \nby 30 June 2023 (see the notice from the EPO dated 13 November 2021, OJ EPO 2021, \nA84). In other cases, the DAS system should be used for exchange of priority documents."
    },
    {
        "question_number": "48",
        "question_text": " \n \nFollowing entry into the EPO regional phase, a translation of the international  \napplication is not filed at the EPO in due time. How can this be remedied? \n \nA.​\nThe applicant can request reinstatement of rights under Rule 49.6 PCT. \nB.​\nThe applicant can file the translation, request further processing and pay the further \nprocessing fee under Rule 135 EPC within two months  \nof notification by the EPO.",
        "answer": "The ideal answer is B.  \nFurther processing should be requested under Article 121 and Rule 135(1) EPC. Option A \ncan be used but, due to the strict requirements and higher fee, it is not appropriate unless the \nperiod for requesting further processing has expired"
    },
    {
        "question_number": "49",
        "question_text": " \n \nThe applicants for international application PCT-1 are based in Japan. Having regard to the \nprovisions of the EPC and the PCT, can the applicants themselves comply with the \nrequirements of Rule 159(1) EPC? \n  \nA.​\nNo, a professional representative must be appointed. \nB.​\nNo, a professional representative or appropriate legal representative must be \nappointed. \nC.​\nYes, the applicants can themselves comply with the requirements of Rule 159(1) \nEPC.",
        "answer": "The correct answer is C.  \nApplicants can themselves comply with the requirements of Rule 159(1) EPC (Euro-PCT \nGuide 15th edition, 2022, 5.3.007 and 5.3.008, Guidelines A-VIII, 1.1). Thereafter, a \nprofessional representative or appropriate legal  \npractitioner must be appointed in accordance with Articles 133(2) and 134 EPC, except for \nthe payment of fees, which may be validly effected by any person (Guidelines A-X, 1)."
    },
    {
        "question_number": "50",
        "question_text": " \n \nA French patent application FP2, including claim 1 related to subject-matter A and claim 2 \nrelated to A+B, is filed validly claiming priority from an earlier French patent application FP1 \nrelated to subject-matter A and filed ten months earlier. \nFP1 is still pending. No relevant prior art has been discovered regarding subject-matter A or \nA+B. Ten months after the filing of FP2, the applicant instructs you to file a European patent \napplication EP1 identical to and claiming priority from FP2 and if possible from FP1. They \nalso ask about the likely outcome of the EP1. What do you tell them, based on our current \nknowledge of the situation? \nA.​\nBoth priority claims are valid and EP1 may be granted with both claims 1 and 2. \nB.​\nEP1 cannot validly claim priority from FP1 but the priority from FP2 is valid and EP1 \nmay be granted with both claims 1 and 2. \nC.​\nEP1 cannot validly claim priority from FP1, which becomes prior art for subject-matter",
        "answer": "The correct answer is C. \nGiven what we know about the prior art, claim 1 will not be granted as it is not novel, whereas \nat this point there is no relevant prior art against claim 2.  \nIt is too late at the filing of EP1 to claim priority from FP1, since approximately 20 months \nhave passed since FP1 was filed. It is also too late to restore the priority under Article 122 \nEPC, which would have had to happen no later than two months after the 12-month time limit \nset by Article 87 (1) EPC. \nFP2 is not a valid priority document for subject-matter A because it was not the first filing for \nit (Article 87(4) EPC), so the effective date of claim 1 of EP1 is the filing date of EP1. \nFP1 is pending, so it follows that it has been published 18 months after its filing, which is \nafter the filing of FP2 but before the filing of EP1, making it part of the prior art under Article \n54(2) EPC for claim 1 in EP1, which is not entitled to priority from FP2. \nThe disclosure of subject-matter A in FP1 takes away the novelty of claim 1 in EP1. \nSubject-matter A+B was disclosed for the first time in FP2, making FP2 the first filing for this \nsubject-matter. The priority claim is therefore valid for A+B. The effective date for claim 2 is \nbefore the publication of FP1, so FP1 cannot be cited as prior art against it."
    }
]